Guide to the New-York Historical Society Celebratory and Memorial Event Records 1854-1954 NYHS-RG 12
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society celebratory and memorial event records
1854-1954
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 12
7.7 Linear feet in 13 document boxes, two card boxes, and one oversize folder.
The New-York Historical Society celebratory and memorial event record group includes correspondence, invitations, event programs, tickets, and other material associated with about twenty of the special events held by N-YHS from 1854-1954. These events included major N-YHS anniversaries, commemorations of Washington Irving (1860) and William Cullen Bryant (1878), the completion of the Central Park West building (1939), and others. The record group also includes documents related to the Robert Fulton exhibition installed at N-YHS in 1909 in conjunction with the Hudson-Fulton Celebration.
Arrangement Note
The record group is arranged by event, in chronological order.
Biographical/Historical Note
Founded in November 1804, the members of the New-York Historical Society would often gather throughout its history to commemorate and celebrate important anniversaries or events. (Not all of these commemorations are represented in this particular record group, so the following note emphasizes in its examples those events for which documents are present. See the Related Material Note for references to other N-YHS record groups with documents concerning commemorative events.)
Certainly one significant and regular gathering marked the annual anniversary of N-YHS itself. N-YHS often sought noteworthy speakers for these anniversaries, such as Charles Francis Adams (1870) and Richard Salter Storrs (1875), who were among those who made addresses on these occasions. In 1925, N-YHS initiated an award "For Achievement in History." The gold medal was presented at N-YHS's anniversary meeting, though it was not awarded every year. Among the recipients were Isaac Newton Phelps Stokes (1925), Wilberforce Eames (1931), DeWitt M. Lockman (1933), and George Clinton Densmore Odell (1942).
Major anniversaries of N-YHS's founding called for more than the usual celebration. The semi-centennial (50th) anniversary included an address by George Bancroft and a dinner at the Astor House. The centennial celebration included a dinner and subsequent toasts and speeches at Delmonico's restaurant, an event that generated controversy as the women members of N-YHS were excluded from the dinner and relegated to the balcony with non-members for the after-dinner orations. The sesqui-centennial (150th) anniversary was a two-part affair, with a dinner in May 1954 for a select group at the Union Club and an address by Columbia University President Grayson L. Kirk, followed in November with a full meeting that included an address by historian Allan Nevins. For both the centennial and sesqui-centennial, commemorative medals were struck and histories of N-YHS were written, both offered for sale.
Aside from its anniversaries, N-YHS also celebrated other events in its institutional history, such as the completion of its building on Central Park West in 1939 (see New-York Historical Society original buildings planning & construction records (NYHS-RG 3) for more information about the history of the institution's buildings), the opening of its new Early American Rooms (1951), and the publication of a biography about the nineteenth century singer Emma Thursby (1940). And N-YHS memorialized its members who had recently died, typically with remarks at a regular meeting of the members, but on occasion at a larger public gathering. In at least one instance, for former Treasurer Robert Schell, N-YHS arranged the publication of a memorial book (1901). Some of these memorial events concerned individuals who were national figures as well as N-YHS members, including Washington Irving (1860) and William Cullen Bryant (1878). Bryant's memorial, held in New York's Academy of Music, was attended by U.S. President Rutherford B. Hayes and members of his Cabinet.
Beyond its own history, N-YHS commemorated important historical events of a national, state or local character, such as the 100th Anniversary of the New York State Constitution (1877) and the 200th Anniversary of the Introduction of Printing in New York City (1893). A significant occasion along these lines was the 1909 joint celebration of the 300th anniversary of Henry Hudson's discovery of the river that would later carry his name and the 100th anniversary of Robert Fulton's successful use of steam for traveling on the Hudson. The overall activities for the weeks-long celebration were coordinated by a Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission, funded by the state, city and private donors. In cooperation with the Commission and other groups, especially the Colonial Dames of America, N-YHS installed the event's official Robert Fulton loan exhibition in its newly-built Dexter Hall. N-YHS was also the location for one of the reviewing stands along the route of the three parades that took place during the late September and early October celebration. After the close of the celebration and the Commission completed its work, it donated its records to N-YHS (the records are available; see manuscript call number MS 314).
Not all events at N-YHS were grand commemorations. Public lecture series, long a staple of N-YHS programming and commonly illustrated with lantern slides, continued in the twentieth century, featuring popular speakers such as Gilbert McClurg, Alvin F. Harlow, and Charles Wellington Furlong in the 1930s and Harry Twyford Peters in the 1940s. But programming also expanded in new directions, including musicales and other concert programs. Some of these musical programs were tied to other events at N-YHS, including to the revivals in 1939 of two nineteenth century N-YHS traditions: the springtime reception called the Strawberry Festival after its featured refreshment and the December celebration of St. Nicholas Day. Beginning in the early nineteenth century, N-YHS often linked the timing of its November anniversary celebrations to the Dutch traditions of St. Nicholas Day in December; in 1939 this tradition was revived with public programming associated with December holiday festivities.
(The principal source for this note was N-YHS Director R.W.G. Vail's Knickerbocker Birthday, published in conjunction with the institution's sesqui-centennial anniversary in 1954. See especially the section "Elegant Dinners and Eloquent Diners" on pages 361-445.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. One document box includes only excess copies of ephemera culled from some of the other folders in the record group; this box of redundant material is available for N-YHS staff use only.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society celebratory and memorial event records (NYHS-RG 12) are as follows:
The New-York Historical Society management committee record group (NYHS-RG 1) holds many documents related to memorials and various events. Many of the events are referenced in the minute books and the "official papers" hold correspondence, arrangement committee notes, tickets, and other matter. Some of this documentation relates to events found in NYHS-RG 12, such as the Washington Irving commemoration, while others events found in NYHS-RG 1 are not represented in NYHS-RG 12, such as the Washington Inauguration Anniversary Commemoration (1839) and the Daniel Webster lecture (1852).
The New-York Historical Society general correspondence record group (NYHS-RG 2) includes the principal files for correspondence of all matters at N-YHS into the twentieth century. These files should be referred to for all correspondence related to events, including ticket requests, invitation replies, responses to election to event committees and delegations, and ephemera such as invitations and programs. In cases of substantial material related to a specific event, items have been grouped and/or noted in the finding aid.
The New-York Historical Society pictorial archive (NYHS-RG 5) includes the oversize seating charts for the 1854 and 1954 anniversary dinners, along with photographs related to the 1954 events. The pictorial archive also includes photographs and other images from other N-YHS exhibitions, programs, and events.
The New-York Historical Society manuscripts of lectures and addresses (NYHS-RG 11) includes the manuscript form of various anniversary addresses, memorials, lectures, and other presentations made at N-YHS over time. Among those relating specifically to NYHS-RG 12 are the toasts and other statements made at N-YHS's 50th and 100th anniversary celebrations, Charles O'Conor's comments on the occasion of the 100th anniversary of the adoption of the New York State Constitution, and speeches made at the receptions for Isaac Newton Phelps Stokes and DeWitt McClellan Lockman.
The New-York Historical Society ephemera record group (NYHS-RG 14) contains invitations, tickets, programs, and other print material related to N-YHS special events.
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society celebratory and memorial event record group includes correspondence, invitations, event programs, tickets, and other material associated with some of the special events held by N-YHS over part of its history. About twenty events are represented in the record group, beginning with the celebration of N-YHS's semi-centennial (50th) anniversary in 1854 and ending with the sesqui-centennial (150th) anniversary in 1954. The inclusion of these events, and not others, in this record group reflects the original organization of the material in N-YHS's archive; the particular criteria, if any, distinguishing these events is not known. (See the Related Materials Note in this finding aid.)
The bulk of the record group includes correspondence, invitation lists, and other documents related to attendance at the events, that is, much of the material consists of acceptances or regrets from N-YHS members and invited guests in response to offers to attend an event. These events include major N-YHS anniversaries (50th, 100th, and 150th), anniversaries featuring major speakers (66th/Charles Francis Adams and 75th/Richard Salter Storrs), presentations of N-YHS's Achievement in History award (to Isaac Newton Phelps Stokes, Wilberforce Eames, DeWitt McClellan Lockman, and George Clinton Densmore Odell), memorials (Washington Irving, William Cullen Bryant), and other N-YHS achievements (completion of Central Park West building, publication of a biography of Emma Thursby, and opening of Early American Rooms). The correspondence for the Bryant commemoration includes an autograph letter signed by U.S. President Rutherford B. Hayes accepting the invitation to attend the event.
There is rich material in the record group concerning N-YHS's installation of the Robert Fulton loan exhibition as part of New York City's 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration. The documents relate principally to the planning for this exhibition, including correspondence and other records of objects loaned to the exhibition. There are also some documents concerning the donation of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission records (MS 314) to N-YHS.
Some of the events include documents concerning the planning for the event itself. These can be found primarily in the case of the major N-YHS anniversaries, the Bryant commemoration, and the William Bradford/Introduction of printing to New York City commemmoration. Although N-YHS's history of lecture series and other public programs do not appear prominently in the record group, there are two folders of documents concerning arrangements for lectures in the 1930s. Some documents concern the preparation of a memorial book for former Treasurer Robert Schell. There are two artifacts from the sesqui-centennial anniversary in the record group: two medals and a steel stamp.
New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Hudson-Fulton Celebration, 1909 -- Exhibitions; Programs (documents).; Invitations.; Correspondence.; Admission tickets.; Eulogies (documents).; Hudson-Fulton Celebration Commission -- Correspondence; New-York Historical Society -- Anniversaries, etc.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives; New-York Historical Society -- Centennial celebrations, etc.
- N-YHS Semi-Centennial (50th) Anniversary. Committee on Arrangements. Minute Book, 1854 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- N-YHS Semi-Centennial (50th) Anniversary. Committee on Arrangements. Loose Sheets from Minute Book, 1854, 1857 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Includes some 1857 clippings related to the dedication of the new 2nd Ave. building.
- N-YHS Semi-Centennial (50th) Anniversary. Committee on Arrangements. Reports, Notes, Etc., 1854 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- N-YHS Semi-Centennial (50th) Anniversary. Correspondence, 1854 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  Includes responses to invitations.
- N-YHS Semi-Centennial (50th) Anniversary. Print Matter, 1854 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes invitations, list of stewards, toasts, Theodore E. Tomlinson's "Tribute to Woman" (response to Luther Bradish's toast), event proceedings, George Bancroft's oration "The Necessity, the Reality, and the Promise of the Progress of the Human Race," and the menu from the Astor House, among other documents.
- N-YHS Semi-Centennial (50th) Anniversary. Documents from after the Event, 1854-1855 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  Documents relate to the distribution of the proceedings and attempts to collect payments on ticket subscription commitments.
- N-YHS Semi-Centennial (50th) Anniversary. Clippings, 1854 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- Washington Irving Commemoration. December Meeting Resolutions, Etc., 1859 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes abstracts, correspondence, and speeches related to the December 6, 1859, N-YHS meeting at which Irving's death was announced, and the resolutions concerning holding a commemorative event in April 1860.
- Washington Irving Commemoration. Correspondence (1 of 5), 1860 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  This set of folders principally includes responses to the invitations for tickets to the Irving celebration. See also: N-YHS General Correspondence (NYHS-RG 2), Series I, for a folder of many letters related to this event, including letters by William Cullen Bryant, Jared Sparks, Martin Van Buren, and others.
- Washington Irving Commemoration. Correspondence (2 of 5), 1860 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Washington Irving Commemoration. Correspondence (3 of 5), 1860 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Washington Irving Commemoration. Correspondence (4 of 5), 1860 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Washington Irving Commemoration. Correspondence (5 of 5), 1860 April (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- Washington Irving Commemoration. Print Matter, 1860 April (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  Includes the featured orator Edward Everett's letter conveying a newspaper clipping of his remarks at the event, with his annotated corrections, event tickets, and other print matter.
- St. Nicholas Festival, 1864 (Box OS-1, Folder 10)
  Includes three copies of the 1864 N-YHS document that reproduced John Pintard's 1810 festival document, with additional engravings. See also: Multiple additional copies of the 1864 reprint are also in the Print Room's Broadside Collection. The Print Room also holds one copy of the original 1810 document; see call number SY1810 no.94.
- 66th Anniversary/Charles Francis Adams Address. Invitations and Tickets, 1870 December (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- 66th Anniversary/Charles Francis Adams Address. Correspondence (Ticket Requests), 1870 December (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- 66th Anniversary/Charles Francis Adams Address. Clippings, 1870 December (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- 70th Anniversary/Richard S. Storrs Address. Correspondence (Ticket Requests) (1 of 4), 1875 April (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- 70th Anniversary/Richard S. Storrs Address. Correspondence (Ticket Requests) (2 of 4), 1875 April (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- 70th Anniversary/Richard S. Storrs Address. Correspondence (Ticket Requests) (3 of 4), 1875 April (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- 70th Anniversary/Richard S. Storrs Address. Correspondence (Ticket Requests) (4 of 4), 1875 April (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- 100th Anniversary of the New York State Constitution. Invitations and Tickets, 1877 May (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- 100th Anniversary of the New York State Constitution. Proceedings and other Notes, 1877 May (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- 100th Anniversary of the New York State Constitution. Correspondence (Ticket Requests), 1877 May (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- William Cullen Bryant Commemoration. Committee on Arrangements (1 of 5), 1878 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes minutes of committee meetings, lists of individuals sitting on the stage for the discourse by George William Curtis, Reception Committee candidates, and other lists.
- William Cullen Bryant Commemoration. Committee on Arrangements (2 of 5), 1878 (Box OS-1, Folder 5)
  Includes two seating charts of the Academy of Music, with some annotations indicating box seat assignments for some individuals.
- William Cullen Bryant Commemoration. Committee on Arrangements (3 of 5), 1878 December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
  Access Restrictions
  The original President Hayes letter is restricted. Researchers will be given a photocopy to use.
  Includes acceptances to attend the event from U.S. President Rutherford B. Hayes and from four Cabinet officials. Includes correspondence between Committee members.
- William Cullen Bryant Commemoration. Committee on Arrangements (4 of 5), 1878 December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  Includes acceptances and regrets concerning invitations to be on the event's Reception Committee.
- William Cullen Bryant Commemoration. Committee on Arrangements (5 of 5), 1874, 1878 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  Includes printed invitations and tickets. The folder also includes two forms of 1874 related to Bryant: a form for subscribing toward funds for a vase in honor of Bryant to be placed in the Metropolitan Museum of Art and a form directed to Bryant informing him of the initiative.
- William Cullen Bryant Commemoration. Correspondence (Ticket Requests) (1 of 2), 1878 December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- William Cullen Bryant Commemoration. Correspondence (Ticket Requests) (2 of 2), 1878 December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
- William Cullen Bryant Commemoration. Clippings, 1878 December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Committee Resolutions & Reports (1 of 2), 1893 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Committee Resolutions & Reports (2 of 2), 1893 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 2)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Correspondence (1 of 2), 1893 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 3)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Correspondence (2 of 2), 1893 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 4)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Invitation Lists, 1893 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 5)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Library Reception Tickets, 1893 May 21 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 6)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Remarks of John A. King, 1893 April 8 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 7)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Research Notes (1 of 2), 1893 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 8)
  This folder and the next include notes regarding N-YHS's research into the location of Bradford's printing office.
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Research Notes (2 of 2), 1893 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 9)
- William Bradford Commemoration (200th Anniversary of Introduction of Printing in New York). Clippings, 1893 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 10)
- Robert Schell Memorial Book, 1901 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  Includes the memorial book produced by N-YHS.
- Robert Schell Memorial Book. German Savings Bank Memorial Book, 1900 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
- Robert Schell Memorial Book. Bank of the Metropolis Memorial Book, 1900 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
- Robert Schell Memorial Book. Minutes and Memorials, 1900 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  Memorials provided for the N-YHS memorial book by: New York University, Presbyterian Hospital, Rutgers College, and Woodlawn Cemetery. Also included is a manuscript form of the N-YHS memorial.
- Robert Schell Memorial Book. Publication Preparation, [1901] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
  Includes a few documents related to the printing of the memorial.
- Robert Schell Memorial Book. Correspondence, 1901 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  Includes acknowledgements from institutions that received one of the distributed memorial books.
- N-YHS Centennial Banquet. Subscriptions (Ticket Purchase Commitments) (1 of 2), 1904 September-November (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
- N-YHS Centennial Banquet. Subscriptions (Ticket Purchase Commitments) (2 of 2), 1904 September-November (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
- N-YHS Centennial Banquet. Correspondence, 1904 November (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
  Includes responses from special invitees and notices from member ticket purchasers of the names of their guests. The correspondence includes signed letters of regret from Woodrow Wilson (then President of Princeton University) and U.S. Secretary of State John Hay. The letters also include two letters of regret sent on behalf of the President from the White House.
- N-YHS Centennial Banquet. Register of Correspondents(?), 1904 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
- N-YHS Centennial Banquet. Arrangements, 1904 September-November (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  Includes documents related to planning aspects of the banquet, especially the design of the commemorative menu (Dempsey & Carroll, designer), seating plan, wine purchases, and lists of attendees.
- N-YHS Centennial Banquet. Print Matter, 1904 September-November (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
  Includes ephemera and other printed items: guest invitation, forms related to ticket subscriptions and purchases, admission tickets to dinner (men only), admission tickets to the balcony (after dinner, women only), wine list, and seating plan. Also includes two silk(?) artifacts.
- N-YHS Centennial Banquet. Commemorative Menu, 1904 November 22 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
- N-YHS Centennial Medal. Correspondence. Victor D. Brenner (Designer), 1903-1904 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
- N-YHS Centennial Medal. Correspondence. Gorham Manufacturing Co., 1904-1905 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
- N-YHS Centennial Medal. Offering Circulars, 1904-1905 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
- N-YHS Centennial Medal. Correspondence. Subscribers (1 of 5), 1904 October (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
- N-YHS Centennial Medal. Correspondence. Subscribers (2 of 5), 1904 October-December (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)